In the last video, you learn about
the GRU, the Gated Recurring Unit and how
that can allow you to learn very
long range connections in a sequence.
The other type of unit that allows you
to do this very well is the LSTM or
the long short term memory units.
And this is even more powerful
than the GRU, let's take a look.
Here the equations from the previous
video for the GRU and for
the GRU we had a t = c t and two gates
the update gate and the relevance gate.
c(tilde) t, which is a candidate for
replacing the memory cell.
And then we use the gate, the update
gate gamma Wu to decide whether or
not to update c t  using c(tilde) t.
The LSTM is an even slightly more powerful
and more general version of the GRU and
it's due to set hook writer and
Jurgen Schmidt Huber.
And this was a really seminal paper,
there's a huge impact on sequence
modeling, although I think this paper is
one of the more difficult ones to read.
It goes quite a lot into
the theory of vanishing gradients.
And so I think more people have learned
about the details of LSTM through maybe
other places than from this particular
paper, even though I think this paper has
had a wonderful impact on
the deep learning community.
But these are the equations
that govern the LSTM, so
the will continue to the memory cell c and
the candidate value for
updating it c(tilde) t  will be this.
And so notice that for the LSTM,
we will no longer have the case
that a t is equal to c t.
So this is what we use and so this is
like the equation on the left except
that with now more use a t there or
a t-1, c t-1 and
we are not using this
gamma r this relevance.
Although you can have a deviation of
the LSTM and we put that
back in but with a more common version of
the LSTM doesn't bother with that.
And then we will have
an update gate same as before.
So w update and
I'm going to use a t-1 here,
ct +bu and
one new property of the LSTM is instead of having one update gate
control
both of these terms, we're going to have two separate terms.
So instead of gamma u and
1- gamma u were going to have gamma u here
and for
gate k we should call gamma f.
So this gate gamma f is going to be
sigmoid of, pretty much what you'd expect.
c t  plus
bf, and then we're going to have a new output gate
which is sigmoid of Wo and then again,
pretty much what you'd expect plus bo.
And then the update value to
the memory cell will be c t equals
gamma u then this asterisk in
those element wise multiplication.
There's a vector vector,
element wise multiplication plus and
instead of one minus gamma u were
going to have a separate for
gate gamma f times c t-1.
So this gives the memory cell the option
of keeping the old value c t-1 and
then just adding to it this
new value c(tilde) t.
So use a separate update and
forget gates right?
So this stands on update.
Forget and output gates and
then finally instead of 80 equals c t.
Is a t equal to the output gate
element wise multiply with c t.
So these are the equations
that govern the LSTM.
And you can tell it has
three gates instead of two.
So it's a bit more complicated and places
against in slightly different places.
So here again are the equations
governing the behavior of the LSTM.
Once again it's traditional to explain
these things using pictures, so
let me draw one here.
And if these pictures are too
complicated don't worry about it,
I probably find the equations easier
to understand than the picture but
just show the picture here for
the intuitions it conveys.
The particular picture here was very
much inspired by a blog post due to
Chris Kohler titled
Understanding LSTM networks.
And the diagram drawn here is quite
similar to one that he drew in his
blog post.
But the key things to take
away from this picture or
maybe that you use a t-1 and
x t to compute all the gate values.
So in this picture you have a t-1 and
x t coming together to compute
a forget gate to compute the update
gates and the computer the output gate.
And they also go through a tarnish
to compute a c(tilde) t.
And then these values are combined
in these complicated ways with element wise multiplies and so on
to
get a c t from the previous c t -1.
Now one element of this is interesting
is if you hook up a bunch of these in parallel
so that's one of them and you
connect them, connect these temporarily.
So there's the input x 1,
then x 2, x 3.
So you can take these units and just hook
them up as follows where the
output a for a period of time,
70 input at the next time set.
And similarly for C and I've simplified
the diagrams a little bit at the bottom.
And one cool thing about this, you
notice is that this is a line at the top that shows how
so long as you said
the forget and the update gates, appropriately,
it is relatively easy for
the LSTM to have some value C0 and
have that be passed all the way to
the right to have, maybe C3 equals C0.
And this is why the LSTM as
well as the GRU is very good at
memorizing certain values.
Even for a long time for
certain real values stored in
the memory cells even for
many, many times steps.
So that's it for the LSTM,
as you can imagine, there are also a few variations
on this that people use.
Perhaps the most common one,
is that instead of just having the gate values
be dependent only on a t-1, xt.
Sometimes people also sneak in
there the value c t -1 as well.
This is called a peephole connection.
Not a great name maybe, but
if you see peephole connection,
what that means is that the gate values
may depend not just on a t-1 but
and on x t but
also on the previous memory cell value.
And the peephole connection can go into
all three of these gates computations.
So that's one common variation
you see of LSTMs one technical
detail is that these are say
100 dimensional vectors.
If you have 100 dimensional
hidden memory cell union.
So is this and so
say fifth element of
c t-1 affects only the fifth element of
the correspondent gates.
So that relationship is 1 to 1
where not every element
of the 100 dimensional c t-1 can affect
all elements of the gates, but
instead the first element of c t-1
affects the first element of the gates.
Second element affects second elements and
so on.
But if you ever read the paper and see someone
talk about the peephole
connection, that's what they mean,
that c t -1 is used to affect
the gate value as well.
So that's it for the LSTM, when should you
use a GRU and when should you use an LSTM.
There is a widespread consensus in this.
And even though I presented GRUs first
in the history of deep learning, LSTMs
actually came much earlier and then GRUs
were relatively recent invention that were
maybe derived as partly a simplification
of the more complicated LSTM model.
Researchers have tried both of these
models on many different problems and
on different problems the different
algorithms will win out.
So there isn't a universally
superior algorithm,
which is why I want to
show you both of them.
But I feel like when I am using these,
the advantage of the GRU is
that it's a simpler model.
And so it's actually easier to build a
much bigger network only has two gates, so
computation runs a bit faster so it scales
the building, somewhat bigger models.
But the LSTM is more powerful and
more flexible since there's
three gates instead of two.
If you want to pick one to use,
I think LSTM has been
the historically more proven choice.
So if you had to pick one,
I think most people today will still use
the LSTM as the default
first thing to try.
Although I think the last few years GRUs
have been gaining a lot of momentum and
I feel like more and
more teams are also using GRUs because
they're a bit simpler but often were,
just as well and it might be easier to
scale them to even bigger problems.
So that's it for LSTMs with either GRUs or
LSTMS, you'll be able to
build new networks that can capture
much longer range dependencies.